Guide to the Leonard and Marjorie Caldwell Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Leonard and Marjorie Caldwell Papers
1921-1983
RG 217
Yale University Divinity School Library
1
(3 boxes)
This collection consists of personal letters, a diary, oral history transcript, printed material, photographs, and memorabilia dating primarly from 1921 to 1926 when Leonard Caldwell was teaching math and physics at the University of Nanking. Caldwell, a Yale graduate, worked as a civil engineer in the U.S. following his return from China. Marjorie Caldwell was a librarian, as well as missionary wife and mother.
Caldwell, Leonard Hathaway
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Polly Caldwell, 2008
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Chronology
1894 Jan 29 Leonard Hathaway Caldwell born in Jacksonville, FL.
1895 Jun 29 Marjorie Russell Rockwood born in Franklin, MA.
1915 LHC graduated from Yale University, Sheffield Scientific School, PhB in Civil Engineering with honors.
1915-1916 LHC did one year of postgraduate work in Sanitary Engineering at Yale.
1917Dec-1919 Jul LHC served in the U.S. Army, Co. K., 23rd Corps of Engineers, A.E.F. in France.
1918 MRR graduated from Simmons College, BS in Library Science.
1918-1921 MRR worked as a library first in Williamstown, MA and from 1919 to 1921 Jul 31 in New Haven, CT.
1920 Fall LHC entered Yale School of Religion.
1921 Sep 5 LHC and MRR were married and departed immediately for China.
1921 Oct - 1926Jun LHC taught at the University of Nanking, initially as head of the Physics department. He also taught math, geology, engineering/surveying.
1921-1926 While in Nanking, MRRC served primarily as a missionary wife, and gave birth to three sons. She also taught a YMCA English conversation course, started a book-reading circle with Pearl Buck and other women in Nanking, and served the libraries of the University of Nanking and Ginling College. The Caldwells lived with the Bucks when they first arrived in Nanking.
1927-1929 LHC worked for Atlanta, GA Contruction Department.
1929-1931 LHC worked for Aerotopograph Corporation of America, Washington, DC.
1932-1938 LHC worked for U.S. Corps of Engineers research unit in Dayton, OH.
1938-1947 LHC worked for Multi-plex Mapping Section of United States Engineers District Office in Little Rock, AR.
1947-1951 LHC was in private practice.
1940s-1977 MRRC returned to work as a librarian in Little Rock, AR.
1957 Jul 13 LHC died in Little Rock, AR.
1990 Jul 20 MRRC died in Seattle, WA.
See Box 1, Folder 8 for more detailed biographical information.
Scope and Contents
Although the Caldwells were in China for less than five years, this collection provides an excellent snapshot of many aspects of the life and work of missionaries. Early letters from Leonard to Marjorie deal with the decision to go to China immediately after their marriage and the concerns of Marjorie's parents. Later letters from the summer of 1925 provide detailed descriptions of Leonard's surveying trip in the Lushan countryside. Marjorie's letters to friends in the U.S. give insight into the daily life of a missionary wife and mother. Typed transcripts of these letters have been prepared by the Caldwells' granddaughter Polly Caldwell. The Caldwells kept in touch with various Nanking missionary colleagues after their return to the U.S. and received letters describing their activities. A diary for 1922, written jointly by Leonard and Marjorie, provides a very detailed day-by-day account of their activities, including Leonard's teaching at the University of Nanking, Marjorie's daily activities, and their Chinese language study. A typed transcript is also available for this diary. The transcript of an oral history interview conducted with Marjorie in 1983 provides additional detailed information about her time in China. Well-identified photographs document a Chinese home, fishing, housing, and other subjects. Collected material includes religious tracts in Chinese and information about the University of Nanking.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence,1921-1942
Series II: Writings and Notes, ca. 1942, n.d.
Series III: Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1921-1983
Missions -- China; Missionaries; Caldwell, Marjorie; Jinling da xue. Nong ye jing ji xi
- Correspondence, 1921-1942; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is divided into two sections:
  Family letters
  Letters to/from others
  - Family letters
    - Letters from Leonard to Marjorie, postcard to her mother - with typed transcripts, 1921 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 1)
      This folder also contains the detailed inventory of the papers prepared by Polly Caldwell.
    - Letters from Leonard to Marjorie while on trip to Ma Wei Shun and Kuling; letters from Marjorie to Leonard, fragment - with typed transcripts, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to/from others
    - A-H, including Dorothy Annable, Florence Hamilton - with typed transcripts of letters written by Marjorie, 1921-1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - I-S, including Bernice Illick, Albert and Celia Steward, George T. Scott, 1930-1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - U-W, incl. Florence Webster, University of Nanking, 1921-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Writings and Notes, ca. 1942, n.d.; Series II
  - By Leonard Caldwell: "Superstitions in China"; "Educational Missions in China"; "The Chinese People", ca. 1942, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - By others: incl. "Chinese New Year Customs" by Dr. Macklin and Dr. Gia; unidentified notes; pamphlet by Pearl Buck "Can the Church Lead?" (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1921-1983; Series III
  - Biographical Information
    - Incl. newsclippings re. Caldwells, typed "Biographical Highlights" sheets for LHC and MRRC; LHC passport (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Original and typed transcript of detailed day-by-day diary written by LHC and MRRC, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Typed transcript of oral interview of MRRC, conducted by her son Robert, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs
    - Loose photographs #1-21 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Photos include a baby tower, funeral procession, Chinese farmers, group photos of Chinese and missionaries incl. Celia Steward and Marjorie Caldwell, Lossing Buck and children, etc. A detailed listing is available in the inventory of the papers located in Box 1 Folder 1.
    - Loose photographs #22-50 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Photos include houses, landscapes,Ming Tombs, group photos and portraits incl. Leonard Caldwell, Language School teachers. A detailed listing is available in the inventory of the papers located in Box 1 Folder 1.
    - Loose photographs #51-57 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Photos include Summer and Winter Palaces, Peking, Chinese scholar in cell of Examination Hall, temple scenes, water buffalo, Caldwell family. A detailed listing is available in the inventory of the papers located in Box 1 Folder 1.
    - Album pages with photographs labeled "At Home with a Chinese Family", "Burden Bearers", "Country Life in China", "Fishing", "Homes", "Rice Planting", "Some of China's Gods", "Typical Street Scenes in Nanking in 1927" (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Matted photo of Marjorie Caldwell with son Ralph and a Chinese woman, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Matted photos of YMCA teachers, Physics faculty of University of Nanking, 1921-1925 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Collected Material
    - Seven religious tracts in Chinese with pictures of New Testament stories, published by the Literature Department, Stewart Evangelistic Fund; three large colored woodcuts of Chinese gods; simplified map of Peking (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - University of Nanking Handbook; Chinese newspaper, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - University of Nanking newsletters, 1927-1946 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Newsletters and articles about China, including "China at War" by Dr. T. F. Tsiang, "Faced with Death All Day" - account of Rev. Dr. Frank Price's survival during Nanking incident, "Did Marshall Feng Act Rightly" by George T. B. Davis, 1928-1946 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Memorabilia from ship voyage back from China on Dollar Steamship Line, greeting cards, envelopes, 1926, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Booklets: "Nanking Directory of Foreign Residents, Etc. and Handbook of Useful Information" [1923], "Romanization of Chinese Personal Names" by Guy W. Sarvis; Language School lesson; notes; "Alphabetical List of [University of Nanking] Students and Faculty in the Junior and Senior Colleges, Fall, 1922", 1922-1924, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Booklets and newsletters: "The Nanking Bulletin of Church and Community" [1926 Jun 12], "Agriculture and Forestry Notes, University of Nanking" [1932 Jun], "From the Looms and the Homes of China" [n.d., published by the Woman's Auxiliary of the University of Nanking - catalog of Chinese crafts for sale], "The China Magazine" [1947 Apr], "When the Methodists Came to China" [ca.1948], 1926-1948, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - University of Nanking, Department of Missionary Training, Special Class for Housewives - Lessons 1-18 [Chinese language lessons for interacting with servants, tradesmen, etc.], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25-28)
    - Book: Historic Lushan: the Kuling Mountains, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Geography of China by Horatio B. Hawkins, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Madame Chiang's Messages in War and Peace - War Messages and Other Selections by May-ling Soong Chiang, ca. 1938 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - The Linguist - publication of the Student Body of the Nanking Language School of the Department of Missionary Training, University of Nanking - 6 volumes, 1922-1926 (Box 3, Folder 32)